חודש טוב *Chodesh tov*, חודש טוב
*Chodesh tov*. Today's דף daf, *daf* is ל"ו *Lamed Vav*. We pick
up with the משנה mishna, *Mishnah* on ל"ה עמוד ב' *Lamed Heh
amud Bet*, so we're a little behind, so let's get cracking. So
we dealt with the first משנה mishna. *Mishnah* that if you agree
to pay or you do pay or you agree to pay, then
you get the, then you, the שומר shomer *shomer*, will get כפל
*kefel* if the גנב *ganav* is found. Which,
now we turn out to another special case about שומרים shomrim *shomrim*,
so let's take a look. השוכר פרה מחברו *Hasocher parah michaveiro*. So
you rented something from your friend. So Charlie, I rented your cow
from you. והשאילה לאחר *Vehishilah leachar*. And then David there said, "Oh
Dov, would you mind lending me that cow that you rented from
Charlie?" And I said, "Sure, no problem." Now, I just want to
pause for a second because the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to
ask, how did I have a right to do that? Is it
presumed that if somebody is watching somebody's object or borrowing somebody's object,
that they have a right to lend it, right, renting it, somebody's
object, that they have a right to, you know, to lend it
out? So that's going to be debated in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
Either there'll be an opinion that yes, you do have a right
to give it to somebody else to watch and to even to
borrow, whatever. The other opinion will be that the original owner actually
gave me permission. It's like when you rent an apartment, you know,
does the lease say you have a right to sublet or you
don't have a right to sublet?
So Charlie, yeah, explicitly gave me the right. So Charlie basically said,
"Dov, you know, I know that you're a nice guy and people
will see you with a cow and they'll ask you to borrow
it. It's okay with me, you know, on my account if you
want to lend it to them during the period you have it
rented." So one way or another, the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is going
to deal with it, but either, but I do, it is, I
am not violating the owner's wishes in my lending it out. Okay,
that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will clarify. Now, what happened? ומתה כדרכה
*Umesa kedarka*. It died naturally. It died of natural causes. ומתה כדרכה
*Umesa kedarka* is in contrast to מתה מחמת מלאכה meisah machamas melachah.
*Mesa machmat melacha*. If it died as a direct result of the
use, then actually that's,
all, everybody's exempt. You know, the שואל sho'el. *shoel* and the שוכר
sokher, *socher* are exempt because you borrowed it to use it, so
it actually is presumed to be that that's alright, that you get,
that if it breaks naturally without any negligence and through normal use,
you actually are off the hook. Okay, but ומתה כדרכה *Umesa kedarka*
is just natural death. So a natural death is an אונס ones
*oness*, right? It's nothing you could have controlled, nothing you could have
prevented, you know, no matter how hard you would have tried. So
the הלכה halacha *halacha* is is that all the שומרים shomrim *shomrim*
are exempt except the שואל shoel. *shoel*. א שואל shoel. *A shoel*
is liable for all things that happen to the object, the borrower,
because he gets all of the benefit and he pays nothing and
he gives nothing to the owner. He has full liability, even if
אונס ones *oness*, even if with acts of God. The only exception
are two. Number one, what I just mentioned, מתה מחמת מלאכה Meisah
machamas melachah *Mesa machmat melacha*, the thing actually dies or breaks through
normal use. And number two, if בעליו עמו *Baalav imo*, if the
owner is working for him at the time. That's a פסוק *pasuk*
in the תורה *Torah*. Okay, we're not going to worry about בעליו
עמו *Baalav imo* right now. Okay, so I borrowed, I rented this
from Charlie, I lent it out to David, now it dies. So
the שואל shoel. *shoel*, David, is liable for that. The שוכר sokher,
*socher*, me, is exempt from that. Okay? So how's that going to
play out? So the משנה mishna *Mishnah* says the following: ישבע השוכר
שמתה כדרכה She-meisah ke-darkah, *Yeshava hasocher shemesa kedarka*. I take an oath
to Charlie that it died naturally and I'm off the hook, because
as a שוכר socher, *socher* I'm exempt
for, you know, for
אונס ones *oness*. והשואל ישלם לשוכר *Vehashoel yeshaleim lasocher*. He pays me.
So I make a pretty profit off of that, okay? I take
an oath to Charlie and he pays, off of somebody else's cow.
So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei *Rabbi Yosei* voices the, gives the voice
to the moral outrage here. אמר רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei's *Amar Rabbi
Yosei*, כיצד הלה עושה סחורה בפרתו של חברו sechorah b'parato shel chavero,
*Keitzad halaz oseh sechorah beparato shel chaveiro*? How does this guy make
business with his friend's cow? How is he getting paid for a
cow that isn't his? Okay, where's the justice in the world? אלא
תחזור פרה לבעלים ראשונים *Ela tachzor parah labaalim rishonim*. Sure David has
to pay, he was a שואל shoel *shoel*, but he was a
שואל shoel. *shoel* of ultimately Charlie's cow. So therefore, even though it
was during the period I had rented it, so he actually is
going to pay Charlie, not me. Yes, Charlie.
So how can the renter take the oath
when he's not the one who's around when the cow died?
Oh no, so it's assuming that he was around. It's assuming that
he, right, so that's an important point. And what do you do,
what does somebody do if they don't know the specifics of how
it died? Right, so that's an important question, which we're not going
to deal with right now, but that's an important question.
And is there something we're also going to deal with because for
me, I don't see the great distinction between it died naturally versus
it died through work or anything, because in some ways dying through
work is worse.
Right, I understand, but it's, assumed, it's considered like, you know, assumed
risk. Like you're okay with that. Like you lend me your hammer
and I'm just totally using it completely naturally. You lend me your
chair and I sit in it and it breaks, okay? Do you
think I should have to pay you because I was a borrower?
But I also don't think, no, I think you should not pay
me either then. In other words.
Okay, fine.
Right, but one is to seem to be assumed risk. By lending
it to me, you're basically saying use it and what happens happens
if you're responsible and you use it. Anyway, I don't want to,
we can't go into that now, okay? But okay, point acknowledged.
Yeah, is there some sort of distinction between whether he, the renter,
lent the cow or sublet it to another person? In other words...
If he rented, then you wouldn't have the scenario because then both
the original lender renter and the second renter would equally be exempt.
You only have the interesting scenario when the second person is a
שואל, shoel. because then he's liable in at a level that the
original borrower is that the renter is not.
Okay, they'd both be they'd both be exempt.
Okay. אמרי רב נחמן- Amrei Rav Nachman now, it's an interesting question
to say if it was a lent- lenting and lending and could
Charlie choose which one of us to collect from? Let's say I
didn't have the money and you had the money. How far does
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei go? Meaning is רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yosei. basic
issue the injustice of it? Like how it's morally, you know, like
intolerable this scenario? Or is his basic issue at the end of
the day, you David have Charlie's cow, not my cow, even though
I was the borrower, right? So an interesting question for רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosei's would be, let's say I borrowed it, you borrowed it,
we have equal liability, it dies, we're both liable, okay, and I
don't have any money. Can Charlie go to you, okay? So that
would be an interesting question within רבי יוסי. Yes.
Let's get back to the תוספות Tosafot on the בעלים ba'alim but
it- it died-
no, it means pay up. תוספות Tosafot on the בעלים ba'alim is
metaphorical. I mean, whatever.
I give him the carcass?
Yeah, but that's not the point. The point- the point is pay-
the money of it goes back to the original owner. Okay. Now,
now,
now, okay, אמר רבידי בר אבין. Amar Rabidi bar Avin. Now I
do want to say because I'll- I'll make this point now because
it doesn't come up in the גמרא Gemara but it really bothers
me, which is: okay, so I rented it from Charlie and I
have a right to lend it out. And let's even say that's
because I'll even give you the best possible scenario of why David
should pay me. David should pay me because during this period of
this month I have it rented, you know, I am let's say
considered one way the רמב"ם Rambam conceptualizes the idea of rental is
it's a קנין הגוף לזמן לפירות. kinyan haguf lizman lapeiros. Did you
get all that? Meaning, I own Charlie's cow for the month, okay,
for its use. But so I'm a quasi-owner of this cow for
a period of time for certain purposes and for a certain duration
of time. Let's even say that, and I lend- and and therefore
during this period that I'm the owner, I lend it to David.
But Charlie is still the owner for the rest of infinity minus
one month, and even during this month, he's still the owner of
the principal of the cow, of the- base- not its use. So
how does David even, you know, pay me the full value of
the cow? My- my stake in the
cow might- okay, that wasn't intentional. My ownership in the cow, the
cow could be worth a thousand dollars, the value of my one
month ownership of it might be worth twenty dollars. How does David
give me a thousand dollars? I don't own a thousand dollar cow.
I own a twenty dollar percentage of a thousand dollar cow. So
I really don't understand. Somehow though, what we're doing is we're just
saying, well, since he got it from you, his obligation, and what
he got from you was a cow, his obligation to me is
as a borrower of a cow getting it from you during the
period I was in control of it, I had rights to it,
and therefore he has to pay me the full amount. So the
גמרא Gemara never really raises the question I just raised. To me
that seems really like wild, okay? Besides רבי יוסי's claim of how
am I making money off of Charlie's cow? Forget that. It's just
like why- he didn't take away from me a thousand dollars. You
know, I- he- only what was lost to me was my twenty
dollar usage of it. But nevertheless, since I had control over the
cow at that time and I gave it to David, David assumed
an obligation to me, and if it dies, he pays me the
full amount. Okay.
But you have title for that month.
Right, but the point is he pays me the full value. Yes,
I hear- I understand. Okay, so now- okay, so let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara אמר ליה רבידי בר אבין לאביי, Amar
lei Rabidi bar Avin l'Abaye, מכדי, michdi,
let's take a look. שוכר במאי קני להאי פרה? Sokher bemai kani
l'hai parah?
How did I, the שוכר, socher take possession of the cow? בשבועה,
Bishvuah, because I made an oath to Charlie and I said, you
know, I'm not- it died and therefore I'm not liable to you.
ונימא ליה משכיר לשוכר, V'neima lei maskir l'sokher, so why doesn't Charlie
just say to me, דל את ודל שבועתך, dal at u'dal shvuatakh,
you know what though, get yourself out of the picture, get your
שבועה shvuah out of the picture. I don't want you, I don't
want your שבועה, shvuah, okay, because your שבועה shvuah basically sort of
gets me the משכיר maskir out of the picture and lets you
deal with, you know, with the second guy. I don't want to
be pushed out of the picture. I want you to go out
of the picture. So don't make your שבועה shvuah to me, which
would get me out of the picture. Get rid of you and
I'll deal directly with the second guy. דל את ודל שבועתך ואנא
משתעינא דינא בהדי שואל, Dal at u'dal shvuatakh v'ana mishteina dina bahadi
sho'el, and I'll deal directly with the שואל. sho'el So why can't
he say that? Okay, so אמר ליה, amar lei, so אביי Abaye
said back to רבידי בר אבין, Rabidi bar Avin, מי סברת שוכר
בשבועה הוא דקקני לה? Mi savrat sokher bishvuah hu dekakani lah?
Who says the שוכר, socher me, I get possession of the cow-
I'm going to go back and unpack that phrase in a minute-
through my שבועה shvuah and that kicks Charlie out of the picture
and lets me deal with David? And then Charlie could say forget
your שבועה, shvuah, I refuse to accept your שבועה. shvuah. No, משעת
מיתה הוא דקני. Misheat mitah hu dekani. From the moment the cow
dies, I basically have owned the cow. It's- I- now it's my
cow, okay, cause you know, and and therefore- so why am I
making a שבועה? shvuah? שבועה כדי להפיס דעתו של בעל הבית. Shvuah
kedei l'hafis da'ato shel ba'al habayit.
שבועה Shvuah is just to appease Charlie. He's
saying what happened,
what- Even if Charlie says forget your שבועה, shvua, he's immediately out
of the picture. As soon as the cow died due to no
negligence of my own, or due to an אונס ones. let's say
because I'm a שוכר, socher as so, you know, imagine there had
been a בית דין Beis Din sitting at that moment that the
cow died. The בית דין Beis Din would have said, okay, Dov
wasn't at fault, it was a natural death, he's exempt to Charlie,
end of story. Okay, so my relationship with Charlie was severed at
that moment. I had no liability from the moment of death if
I wasn't at blame. Oh, I owe him a שבועה shvua because
he doesn't know that I had no liability. He's upset or whatever.
But the reality is I had no no obligation to him starting
at that moment. My my relationship with him, any obligation severed at
that moment. So therefore, he can't he can't resume his relationship with
the שואל. sho'el He was out of the picture from the moment
it died. Now I've tried my best to explain the גמרא Gemara.
and you notice that in the course of explaining this, I did
not use the words that the גמרא Gemara uses, which when do
I take possession of the cow? Because I don't understand what this
means, I take possession of the cow. First, I don't take possession
of the cow. Charlie first of all gets his dead carcass the
dead carcass back. I don't get the carcass. Where do we ever
get this idea that the שוכר socher when the cow dies now
owns the cow? Like I don't even know where that idea is
coming from. At most we discussed earlier that if I pay the
original owner, maybe that's a type of taking possession of the cow.
So I really I really struggle with this גמרא Gemara and I
really I'm paraphrasing the phrase when do I own the cow to
mean when does my relationship with Charlie end, and Charlie's out of
the picture. So the first idea was Charlie is only out of
the picture when I make a שבועה. shvua. Then and therefore Charlie
can say don't make your שבועה, shvua, I'm still in the picture,
I'm still here, my presence in this whole relationship is as the
original owner and I'm going to deal directly with the second guy,
with the שואל. sho'el. And the response is no, Charlie's out of
the picture from the moment the cow dies and I wasn't liable,
I wasn't negligent, it was an אונס ones, or whatever, then any
Charlie has no claims on anybody. And since Charlie has no claims
on anybody from that moment, okay, yes, I can make a שבועה
shvua to him because he has a claim because he's, you know,
הפיסת דעת hafisa da'as to appease him, but he has no monetary
claim on anybody, and therefore I deal directly with the שואל. sho'el
That's my best attempt at paraphrasing the גמרא Gemara so it makes
some sense.
Yes, you had this idea of the connection between מיתה misa and
קניין. kinyan. Right, in קידושין Kiddushin when the husband dies since הקדוש
ברוך הוא Hakadosh Baruch Hu is מקנה, makneh, it's kind of interesting.
Right. And that has to do with status, right?
Yeah, maybe. Right, right. The problem here, even besides the question I
raised, which is whoever says that the שוכר socher is קונה koneh
it, is even if he is קונה koneh it, he's קונה koneh
it at the moment of death. But the שואל's sho'el obligation to
him had to come from the fact that it was seen as
the שוכר's Socher, cow from earlier, right? So it's not really קונה
koneh here, this can't really mean that. What it really just means
is what what gets the original the משכיר maskir out of the
picture. As long as the משכיר maskir is seen as a claimant
here to the case, he can go straight to the שואל. shoel
But if somehow he's seen as, oh, it died, it wasn't my
fault, you're out of the picture, so you no longer a you
have no claim, and once you have no claim, I get to
deal directly with the שואל. Shoel, That seems to be the point
of the גמרא. Gemara Let's keep on going. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, now if you thought that was complicated, let's let's
look at this. אמר רבי זירא Amar Rabbi Zeira says רבי זירא,
Rabbi Zeira, פעמים שהבעלים משלמים כמה פרות לשוכר. Pe'amim sheba'alim meshalmim kama
paros lasocher.
There are times where Charlie here can wind up paying me the
renter many cows for his cow. Okay, how's this going to work?
היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's the case? אגרה מיניה מאה יומי, Agrah
minei me'ah yomei, I rented it from Charlie for a hundred days,
והדר שאילה מיניה תשעים יומי, vehadar shaylei minei tishim yomei,
and then Charlie says, Dov, I know I rented it to you,
you paid me a nice, you know, renter's fee, hundred bucks for
a hundred days, but I really, really need the cow back. Can
you lend it back to me? So rather than,
I'm now going to lend it back to Charlie. Okay, so שאילה
מיניה תשעים יומי. shaylei minei tishim yomei. And then after five days,
I'm a nice guy, I lent it back to him. Then הדר
אגרה מיניה שמונים יומי, hadar agrah minei shmonim yomei, and then I
say, you know what, Charlie, I shouldn't have done that. I really
need the cow. So actually, could I re-rent it from you? Because
you now have the rights for the next ninety days. Okay, can
I re-rent it from you for for the next eighty days? And
Charlie agrees. שמונים יומי. Shmonim yomei.
And you paid him שכר sachar for the full hundred days, and
now you're also paying
him שכר sachar again on top? Yeah, because I because I was
willing to sacrifice ninety days of that, and now I want to
buy it back, what I sacrificed.
You didn't make him
give you back that money? No, he doesn't give me back the
money. I don't say let's reverse my nice deal my nice thing
of of lending it to you. No, I lent it to him.
He now has rights for the next ninety days. Okay, I sacrificed
ninety days of my usage. And now I want to get it
back. He should be a nice guy maybe and lend it back
to me, but no, he's not a nice guy. So if I
want to get it back from him, I have to rent it
from him again. Okay, so הדר אגרה מיניה שמונים יומי. hadar agrah
minei shmonim yomei. Then Charlie comes back to me and Charlie says,
Dov, I I really still need it. והדר שאילה מיניה שבעים יומי.
vehadar shaylei minei shivim yomei. And he borrows it now for seventy
days. days. Okay. So basically I have two rentals from Charlie, he
has two borrowing, I rented it from him twice, he's borrowed it
from me twice. At the end of the day, the net result
is, okay, the net result is that I have a right for
20 days of rental use, right? I borrowed it for 100, I
lent it back for 90, I borrowed it, so I still have
10 days of use that's left to me.
I rented it for 80, I lent it back for 70, so
that gives me another 10 days of use. I have 20 days
of use, but I have two rental agreements, I have two borrowing,
but I have in this course of this, I have like, wait,
who am I? Maybe you should just, I'm the renter, right, I've
got to put them both, I have two rental agreements. Okay, thank
you, that's a good idea. Okay.
Is that one on the internet, who am I? Who am I?
Okay.
Anyway, so, okay, so רש"י Rashi אוקי בתרי, oki betrei, רש"י Rashi
has שמעון Shimon as the owner
and ראובן Reuven as the borrower, okay, or as the renter. Okay.
So here's the cow.
You like my cow? Okay, anyway, here's the cow, that's my generic
four-legged animal, I got to tell you.
It's the dog from last week.
Okay, from what from last week? The dog.
Here's the cow. Okay, so he rents it to me for 100
days, rents for 100, I lend back for 90,
okay, then he rents it to me for 80,
and I lend back for 70,
okay. So basically what we've got here, there's four transactions, okay, I
have here,
maybe it'll be better right here,
I'll draw this longer, okay. Anyway, so we'll do it like this:
lent for 90, rent for 80, and I lent for 70. Okay,
he must
have had a lot
of time on
his
hands.
Lent for 70.
So
how much, how much time do I have? When I lent this
for 90, I still have 10 days of rental here, that's left
to me, okay. He gave it back to me for 80, which
gave me, wait a minute, he 80 and
the 70 is another 10 days.
I know, no, no, no, no, no, I lent him for 90,
he rented it back to me for 80, oh, so he kept
10 days in that scenario, but he kept 10 days to himself,
sorry. So
he kept 10 days to himself, which isn't really our issue, but
okay, but he kept 10 days to himself, okay. And then I
lent it to him for 70. So, okay, so I have 10
days of rental here and 10 days of rental here, okay. So
I still retain 20 days of rental rights, okay, and it's been
rented twice and lent back twice. Okay. All right.
Now, he's owning the cow, you still
own use of the cow.
Use of the cow, right, for 20 days. Exactly.
Now, right, okay, let's see what happens. Okay, ומתה בתוך ימי שאילתה.
Umeisah Betoch Yemei She'ilatah. Okay,
and then it dies
during some of the period that the original owner, like it dies
after this transaction, it died during these 70 days, okay, when I
still had a right to get it back eventually after he was
done with his 70 days, I had a right to get it
back for 20 more days of rental. Okay. דכולא שאילה ושאילה מחייב
חדא פרה. Dechula She'ilah VeShe'ilah Mechayev Chada Parah.
So now Charlie has to pay me because he borrowed the cow
twice, so therefore he, so for he, so he has to pay
me and it died, so a cow he borrowed from me, although
I had rented it from him, a cow he borrowed from me
died. So if a cow he borrowed from me died, you have
to pay me for the cow. But he borrowed the cow twice,
okay, and those were separate acts of borrowing because each one entitled
him to time the other one didn't entitle him to. So therefore,
they are considered to be separate transactions and each one demands full
payment.
It's like, let me understand, I mean, you only rented, what? It's
like it's a different
cow each, it's like it's a different cow and, it, what? Only
one cow died. I understand, which is going to be the גמרא's
Gemara response, okay. And not only, not only,
not only does he pay me, not only does he pay me
twice for the cow that died, he also has to give me,
the way the גמרא Gemara frames it, which doesn't make any sense,
two cows to use, each one for 10 days so I can
get my 20 days of rental out of it. Okay, which is
crazy because you would say once I have a cow why don't
I use that cow? So the basic logic here is, okay, which
is that you don't look, there's the only way to make sense
of this.
You don't look at the payment of the cow as giving me
back the cow. Because if the payment of the cow was giving
me back the cow, he gave me back the cow once. He
doesn't have to give it to me twice, even though ironically he's
the original owner, but let's see... bracket that. He gave me a
cow; there was only one cow here. You don't look at it
that way. You look at it as, imagine it's almost like a
bet, okay? Like it's just a contract, okay, that's not about paying
the cow. It's a condition. If the cow dies, I will pay
you the full I will pay you the full amount of the
cow. So if you imagine, I mean, with every borrowing agreement, there's
a side agreement that says if the following things happen, I'll pay
you for it. So the following thing happened, and there were two
separate contracts, there were two separate agreements. In each contract, the thing
died, so he has to pay me for it in each one.
So if it's true, we all say, why should I look at
it that way? Right? It's about, I lost your cow, I replaced
your cow. But the only way to make sense of this is
that you look at the obligation of a שומר shomer not so
much as a replacing of the object, but as just with every
with that transaction of borrowing or renting, there's essentially an agreement that
if x, y, and z happens, I will pay you. So there
were then two transactions, two agreements; he pays me twice. It's a
crazy idea, but that's what the that's what the גמרא gemara is
saying.
At what point where on that timeline does the cow die?
During these 70 days, when
after all of
that has happened, yes, exactly. Okay, so there were two lend there
were two borrowing agreements. Maybe I should do B for borrowing. What?
Does this discussion happen all on the same day?
What do you mean, back and forth? No, could be day after
one after another,
but not after the 20 days.
Yeah, yeah, exactly, exactly. So since there were two borrowing agreements, with
each borrowing agreement comes the consequence that if the animal dies, you
pay in full. That's just a consequence of the borrowing agreement, okay,
even though he's borrowed it and returned it already.
Yeah, well, once and re-rented it, right. He borrowed it and then
he and then he re-rented it and that required because okay, then
you sacrificed your rights for those 80 days, but then you borrowed
it again.
What do you not understand?
Because if he already had it for the 10 days and then...
no, he didn't already. All this back and forth happened on let's
say one day. And now I've got a right to renter's rights
to 20 days of rental, okay? And now but for the next
sort of like, you know, 80 days here, or certain whatever, you
know, it's going to be the original owner's possession.
But the cow doesn't die there, it dies up at the beginning,
before any of this is actually happened.
Yeah, I mean these right, these agreements have happened, right.
So if I say I'm going to rent you my cow for
tomorrow starting tomorrow for the next 20 days and then that cow
dies tonight,
yes, before the rental agreement starts? No, then you then you have
to buy a cow and and rent it to me, right. I
mean that's an interesting question, right, that's you know that's an interesting
question actually. Would you still be responsible? I guess so, I mean
that's implicit here, right, that's implicit right, that's implicit here though you're
right that once if I rented it to you and it died
then I have to replace it to you before right I have
to replace... Yeah, that's a good point.
Even before it starts, you would think that like all he has
to do is give the renter maybe at most give him his
money back and a cow to use.
I understand. All right, look, I'm glad that everybody everybody is really
you know riled up and upset. I agree, I don't understand this,
but we're going to go on. We understand what we don't understand,
okay? We understand what the גמרא Gemara is saying, even though we
don't agree with it. Fine, let's move on.
I want one of the deals for the cow, but okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay.
So אמר ליה רב אחא מדפתי.
Amar lei Rav Aha mi-Diphti.
So anyway, all of your frustration is given voice by רב אחא
מדפתי. Rav Aha mi-Diphti. Said רב אחא מדפתי
לרבינא, Rav Aha mi-Diphti l'Ravina, מכדי, Michdi, let's take a look. חדא
פרה היא, Chada para hi, it's one cow! עיילה ואפקה, Ayala v'apka,
he brought it in and he took it out. אפקה משכירות ועיילה
לשאילה. Apka mis'chirut v'ayala l'she'ila. He took it out you know he
you know he took it out from rental and put it into
a borrowing agreement. אפקה משאילה ועיילה לשכירות. Apka mishe'ila v'ayala lis'chirut. He
took it out of a borrowing agreement and put it into a
rental agreement. So you know, whatever, these are just. So he's basically
saying you pay him one cow.
So you pay him or you just...
no, you still pay him, still the case of the Mishna which
is
ironically סחורה בפרתו של חברו, but at the end of the day,
right, Charlie borrowed his own cow back, he pays me. But it's
not that there are two borrowing agreements. Okay, every next one supplanted,
replaced the previous one. It's actually two different arguments. One argument is
it's one cow, it's sort of means like by paying me for
the one cow, he's totally made me whole in a way. So
you can't there are not multiple cows that I lost. Right, the
other one sort of is like one the next one agreement supplants
the next. It's moot to talk about the first borrowing agreement when
it was supplanted by a rental, which was then supplanted by a
borrowing agreement. Okay, anyway. The owner...
understands this? I don't know.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, ומי איתא לפרה בעיניה? u'mi ita l'para b'eina?
דנימא ליה הכי? dinima lei hachi? No. If he was actually handing
the cow back, you could say I don't owe you two cows,
I only owe you one cow, here's the cow. But the cow
isn't physically present. What you have is a liability. And yes, you
could have multiple liabilities for the same for the same thing. It's
like taking out multiple insurance policies for the same object. Okay, and
it's by the same insurer. I don't know if you could do
that. Like I could take out multiple insurance policies from different insurers,
so I could take out multiple insurance policies from the same... insurer.
Okay? And that's what you have here. Okay.
So if the פר par was there,
then just give back the cow, obviously.
So according to him, if you swore, you'd have to pay him
eight ten? What? Like let's say it was a גניבה geneivah and
you swore to him, you'd have to pay him ten?
I don't understand, I'm not dealing with what ifs now, it's complicated
enough. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר מר בר רב
אשי Amar Mar Bar Rav Ashi אין לה עליהן אלא שתי פרות.
ein lah aleihen ela shetei parot. So Mar Bar Rav Ashi goes
back to the רב אחא מדפתי Rav Acha mi-Difti said give me
a break, just give him two cows. חדא דשאילה, Chada de-she'eilah, one
I borrowed, Charlie borrowed his own cow back from me, so he
has to give me a cow because that's the obligation of a
שואל shoel and I get to keep it fully, even which is
again the irony of the משנה, mishna that I only had 100
days use of a cow and now I get a full cow
in exchange, but fine, he was a שואל shoel back of his
own cow and he has to now replace it. וחדא דשכירות, ve-chada
de-sechirut, and then he has to give me another cow to use
not as his obligation for the cow was lost, but as the
fact that he rented me the cow and his rental agreement requires
him to still give me a cow to use under the rental
agreement for 20 days independent of his liability to me as a
שואל. shoel. Okay? So you have this back and forth which conceptually
I think, I mean the opinion that you pay multiple cows is
wild, but I think that it is interesting. Do we understand that
a שומר's shomer. obligation is to restore the object and when the
object is lost the money represents the giving the object back, or
does the money more just represent a payment, a liability, and it's
not the giving back of the object to the point that you
could have multiple payments for the same object? Okay, so if I
want to let me ask it to you in a way that's
the simpler case is not the original owner pays somebody else, it's
I pay the original owner. Let's say I borrowed it from
Charlie and Charlie said Dov, I really need it, let me actually
rent it back from you. So I rented it back to him
or whatever. And then during and then I borrowed it back from
him again. Okay, so now I have two borrowing agreements on the
same cow and the cow died. How many cows do I owe
Charlie? Okay, that's a simpler case. I had his cow, but I
borrowed it twice during the same period because I had to because
I gave it back to him. And this is the debate, do
I owe him one cow or do I owe him two cows?
Okay, how much is the liability of a שואל shoel to replace
the object and we look at the money as I'm giving him
back his object, and how much is it a liability and I
can take out two contracts, essentially two insurance policies on the same
thing?
Yeah, it's like an indemnity.
No, I mean, no, it's like two insurance policies.
Yeah, there's nothing that prevents you from insuring the same thing multiple
times in secular law.
Exactly. But normally here we assume that the nature of שומרים shomrim.
is not an insurance policy. The nature of שומרים is I want
my object back, you have to protect it, make sure I get
it back. If you did not protect it well enough, then you
have to make me whole, but so it's funny to look at
it as though there could be multiple payments. Anyway, let's go on.
That's clearly what the debate is. Okay, וחדא משום שאילה אחת היא
ומשום שכירות אחת היא. ve-chada mishum she'eilah achat hi u-mishum sechirut achat
hi.
All the שאילות she'eilas is one, all the שכירות sechirut is one.
At the end of the day, I'm a שואל shoel and a
שוכר socher and I have rights and you don't look at multiple
שאילות she'eilas for each or multiple שכירויות sechirutos for each cow, it
all reduces essentially to one. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: וחדא דשאילה קני לגמרי, ve-chada de-she'eilah kani legamrei,
so the one now that Charlie has borrowed back his own cow
from me, he has to pay me because it died. He only
pays me one cow according to this. Now that cow I own
full. That was because, even though it was his own cow he
was borrowing back. וחדא דשכירות עביד ביה ימי שכירותיה ומהדר ליה למריה,
ve-chada de-sechirut avid beih yemei sechiruteih u-mahadar lei le-mareih, and the one
that of the cow that represents the rental agreement, I use for
my 20 days of rental and then I give it back to
Charlie. Yeah, Charlie gets one back. Charlie gets one back, I use
one for 20 days and I get one that is the payment
agreement to me. But anyway, that's the idea of give me a
break, you cannot have multiple liabilities for the same object.
Okay. אמר רבי ירמיה פעמים ששניהם בחטאת. Amar Rabbi Yirmiyah pe'amim she-sheneihem
be-chatat. That was the hard one. Now it gets a lot easier.
פעמים ששניהם בחטאת. Pe'amim she-sheneihem be-chatat. Now, forget the case we just
dealt with about me and the owner and multiple exchanges. Let's go
back to the easy case of the משנה. mishna, This is all
to make the משנה Mishnah. easier. The easy case of the משנה
which is I rented from Charlie and I lend it to David.
Okay, now it dies. So David has to make a שבועה shevuah
to me, I have to make a שבועה shevuah to Charlie. That's
the case in the משנה, right? So here comes רבי ירמיה Rabbi
Yirmiyah and say I'm going to give some fun scenarios where we're
going to see that David and I make different types of שבועת
שקר shevuat sheker and we can have different types of קרבנות. korbanot.
And the basic principle is going to be the following. If I
make a סתם שבועת שקר, stam shevuat sheker, I bring a חטאת.
chatat. Okay, I swear that this table was made out of gold,
okay, and I bring a חטאת, chatat, that's a שבועת שקר. shevuat
sheker. All right, if I make a שבועת שקר shevuat sheker that
allows me to profit monetarily, I swear to you I don't owe
you money and I really do owe you money, then I bring
an אשם. asham. Okay, that's what we learned at the end of
בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, I add a fifth, I bring an אשם,
asham, it's a different type of a קרבן. korban. So David owes
a שבועה shevuah to me, I owe a שבועה shevuah to Charlie.
We're now going to deal with scenarios where we all David and
I are consistently making שבועת שקר, shevuat sheker, but based on the
circumstances, sometimes we will profit by... and we'll both have to bring
an אשם, Asham, sometimes we won't profit by it and we'll both
have to bring a חטאת, Chatas, sometimes one of us will profit
and one won't, and the one who profited by it brings an
אשם Asham and the one who didn't profit by it brings a
חטאת. Chatas. Okay? So let's take a look. פעמים ששניהם בחטאת, Pe'amim
she-shneihem be-Chatas, sometimes both of them will bring a חטאת, Chatas, פעמים
ששניהם באשם, Pe'amim she-shneihem be-Asham, or sometimes both an אשם, Asham, פעמים
שהשוכר בחטאת, Pe'amim she-ha-socher be-Chatas, top of קו עמוד א', Kuf vov
amud aleph, והשואל באשם, ve-ha-shoel be-Asham, sometimes the שוכר's socher חטאת Chatas
and the שואל's shoel אשם, Asham, פעמים שהשוכר באשם Pe'amim she-ha-socher be-Asham
והשואל בחטאת ve-ha-shoel be-Chatas and sometimes the reverse. הכיצד? Hakeitzad? What's the
case? כפירת ממון, Kfiras mamon, when the oath is a way of
rejecting a monetary obligation and then you admit to it or whatever
you were lying, you bring an אשם. Asham. ביטוי שפתים, Bitui sefasayim,
a simple false oath with no profit, חטאת, Chatas, you bring your
חטאת. Chatas. Now, פעמים ששניהם, Pe'amim she-shneihem, very nice that he gives
us the basic principle right up front. פעמים ששניהם בחטאת כגון, Pe'amim
she-shneihem be-Chatas kegon, okay, which means we didn't profit by our false
oath. שמתה כדרכה, it died naturally. ואמרו נאנסה, Ve-amru ne'enasa, and we
said it was struck by lightning, some other אונס happened. Okay? So
we're lying about the facts, but that doesn't change the substantive reality
that it's an אונס. And in a case of an אונס, David
is liable and I'm exempt. Okay? So we all take an oath,
which doesn't change substantively whether we're liable or not, but we lie
about the facts for whatever reason.
Okay? This is the point, could you tell it's just meant better?
Right, I guess we're embarrassed or something. שוכר, Socher, so when I
take this false oath to Charlie, בין כך ובין כך פטור פטור,
Bein kach u-vein kach patur patur, whether it died naturally or struck
by lightning I'd be exempt, so I'm not getting off of any
liability. בחטאת, Be-Chatas, I'm going to go ahead and have to bring
a חטאת. Chatas. Okay? שואל, shoel now David, בין כך ובין כך
חייב חייב, Bein kach u-vein kach chayav chayav, whatever happened to it
he's חייב chayav to me. So he's taking an, now why is
he taking an oath to me if he's paying? Okay, because you
might remember what we touched on yesterday, that he has to take
an oath of אינו ברשותו. eino bi-reshuso.
Okay? That he's not really holding onto it for himself. Okay? And
since he's saying an oath he's not holding on to it for
himself, in that oath he's saying where is it, what did happen
to it. Okay? So he has to swear what happened to it
even if he's going to pay me, but whatever he says he's
going to pay me, so he didn't gain from it. So בחטאת,
be-Chatas, he also brings a חטאת. Chatas. פעמים ששניהם באשם, Pe'amim she-shneihem
be-Asham, there's a time they both bring an אשם. Asham. כגון
שנגנבה, Kegon she-nignava, okay, it was stolen. If it was stolen it
means that I'm liable also. So we're both liable. ואמרו מתה מחמת
מלאכה, Ve-amru meisah machamas melachah, but we said is that it died
through normal use and dying through normal use, not only am I
exempt, even David is exempt. Even a שואל Sho'eil is exempt by
מתה מחמת מלאכה. meisah machamas melachah, So the reality is we're both
liable and we're taking an oath each of us that we're exempt.
Okay? Because, got it? מתה meisah. מחמת מלאכה even a שואל is
exempt. דתרווייהו קכפרי ממונא, De-tavaihu ka-kafrei mamona, they're both rejecting their monetary
obligation. דמחייבי De-mechayvei because by גניבה gneivah everybody is חייב, chayav, the
שוכר socher and a שואל. וקפטרי נפשייהו Ve-ka-potrei nafshaihu and they're exempting
themselves. So therefore we both bring an אשם. Asham. שוכר בחטאת ושואל
באשם, Socher be-Chatas ve-shoel be-Asham, what's a case that the שוכר socher
is a חטאת Chatas and the שואל is an אשם? Asham? כגון
שמתה כדרכה, Kegon she-meisah ke-darkah, it died naturally. ואמרו מתה מחמת מלאכה,
Ve-amru meisah machamas melachah, but we said it died through use. Now
when it died naturally I'm anyway exempt. But David is חייב. chayav.
Now we're both going to lie and say it died through natural
use. So that lie isn't helping me, I was anyway פטור. patur.
But it is helping David. Because natural death he's חייב, chayav, dying
through use he's פטור. patur. שוכר, Socheir so me, בין כך ובין
כך פטור פטור, Bein kach u-vein kach patur patur, whether it was
natural or through use I'd be exempt. בחטאת, Be-Chatas, I'm going to
go ahead and have to bring a חטאת. Chatas. I swore falsely,
but it was no gain. שואל דמחייב במיתה כדרכה, Shoel de-mechayav be-misah
ke-darkah, the שואל who is חייב chayav when it died naturally. וקפטר
נפשיה במתה מחמת מלאכה, Ve-ka-patar nafshiah be-meisah machamas melachah, he's exempting himself
because when he says that it was מתה מחמת מלאכה, that it
was through use, באשם, be-Asham, so that oath has monetary gain, he
brings an אשם. Asham. What, yeah?
So you're learning something about the קרבנות korbanos then, as in an
אשם Asham is for a weightier or deeper transgression?
Yeah, it's a false, well at least in this case. Yeah. And
it also comes with an additional fifth. Yes. Jenna?
He's חייב chayav when it died naturally and פטור patur if he
dies through use.
Yeah, you came late. I know, that's a little ironic. But when
lightning strikes it a שואל is חייב, chayav, but because he was
borrowed it to use it there was a presumed acceptance of risk
on the part of the owner if something happened through normal use.
Okay? Now, באשם. be-Asham.
שוכר באשם ושואל בחטאת, Socher be-Asham ve-shoel be-Chatas, the last case is
that I the שוכר socher, bring an אשם Asham and David brings
the חטאת. Chatas. כגון שנגנבה, Kegon she-nignava, it was stolen, so now
stolen we're all
liable. ואמרו מתה כדרכה, Ve-amru meisah ke-darkah, that it died naturally. So
that gets me out of my liability. The difference between stolen and
dying naturally. שוכר הוא דמחייב בגניבה ואבידה, Socher hu de-mechayev be-gneivah va-aveidah,
the שוכר socher who's obligated in גניבה gneivah and אבידה. aveidah. וקפטר
נפשיה במתה כדרכה, Ve-ka-patar nafshiah be-meisah ke-darkah, he's exempting himself by saying
it died naturally. באשם, Be-Asham, he, that was a monetary gain. שואל
דבין כך ובין כך הוה מחייב, Shoel de-bein kach u-vein kach havah
mechayev, the שואל that either way is חייב chayav whether it's גניבה
gneivah or מתה. בחטאת, Be-Chatas, he swore falsely and he doesn't gain
anything. Alright, that was fun, and it got us through a lot
of דף, but מאי קא משמע לן? mai ka mashma lan? What
does any of this teach us? It's like we know the basic
rules about when you bring a חטאת Chatas and when you bring
an אשם. Osham. So the גמרא Gemara says no, לאפוקי מדרבי אמי.
le’apukei mid’Rabbi Ami. All of this is to show you that we
reject Rabbi Ami, דאמר d’amar כל שבועה שהדיינים משביעין אותה kol sh’vuah
she’hadayanim mashbi’in osah אין חייבין עליה משום שבועת ביטוי. ein chayavin aleha
mishum sh’vuas bituy. Any any oath imposed by the court, you never
would bring a חטאת. Chatas. If it's imposed by the court, an
oath where you bring a חטאת Chatas is if, you know, is
if Eli and I here are having an argument and I say
"Yeah, that's that's pure gold this table" and Eli says "Ah, you're
making it up," but I take an oath. Okay, that's the type
of an oath that I bring a חטאת. Chatas. But a court-imposed
oath is never the normal is never the חטאת Chatas for the
שבועת ביטוי. sh’vuas bituy. So it might be that it'll be no
חטאת, Chatas, it'll be אשם Osham or nothing. Okay, right. שנאמר Shene’emar
as it says, או נפש כי תשבע לבטא בשפתים, O nefesh ki
sishava l’vatai bisfasayim, if a soul swears to enunciate with his lips.
כי תשבע Ki sishava מאצמו. me'atzmo. He's doing it on his own
initiative. But if it was imposed by the court, that's not what
the case of a חטאת Chatas for a שבועת שקר sh'vuas sheker
is about. קא משמע לן דלא כרבי אמי. Ka mashma lan d’lo
k’Rabbi Ami. We don't rule like Rabbi Ami.
Okay, איתמר. itmar. Fine. That's the end of those of those
scenarios about the back and forth between the owner and, you know,
the שואל and שוכר socher, multiple layered agreements, or the חטאת Chatas
and אשם, Osham, which is bit of I digress. Now we get
to some with all the very two very nice,
juicy, conceptual debates about שומרים. Okay, one is a discussion of I'll
just, you know, tell you, שומר שמסר לשומר. shomer she’masar l’shomer. If
I'm if I'm watching something and I give it to somebody else
to watch, have I violated the, you know, my responsibility to my
owner by handing off the watching out to somebody else? That's שומר
שמסר לשומר shomer she’masar l’shomer and that's going to be followed by
a discussion of תחלתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס. techilaso bifshi’ah v’sofo b’ones. If
I start with an act of negligence and then something accidental happens,
am I liable because of my original negligence? Okay, two very nice
conceptual core סוגיות. sugyos. Let's take a look. איתמר, Itmar, it was
said. שומר שמסר לשומר. Shomer she’masar l’shomer. רב אמר פטור ורבי יוחנן
אמר חייב. Rav amar patur v'Rabbi Yochanan amar chayav. Rav says you're
פטור. patur. Now, פטור patur for what?
Because the owner's acquiesced?
No, not the owner's acquiesced. Okay, so Eli gave me this object
to watch and I said David, and I said here, you know,
David, I gotta go watch my kids or whatever, can you just
watch this object for me? Okay, and he watches it for me.
Okay, has that so Rav says פטור. patur. Now what Rav means
like פטור patur is, is that is that the act of giving
it to David did not increase my liability. I have the same
liability I would have always had. So, okay, if I'm a שומר
שכר shomer sachar I have that level of liability, my שומר חנם
shomer chinam I have that level of liability. Giving it to David
did not in any way increase my liability. Okay, רבי יוחנן אמר
חייב. Rabbi Yochanan amar chayav. No, the very act of giving it
to David—or
decrease it for that matter.
Right, right, yes. The very act of giving it to David means
that I violated my responsibility to Eli there, to the original owner,
and therefore I am liable for anything that happens. Now we're going
to see in a bit it's not totally anything, but anything that
in some way can be attributed to the fact that I wasn't
watching it. Okay? So even if it was a bolt of lightning,
if the bolt of lightning was in David's backyard and not my
backyard, right, that could in some way be attributed to that. Okay,
if it were something that I don't know, it died of cancer,
okay, and the doctors do a post-mortem and see that it died
of cancer, then it can't—then I'm still off the hook. Okay, but
the act of giving it to David was seen as a of
a violation of my responsibility to the owner and if anything happens
after that that in can in any way be attributed to the
fact that I wasn't watching it, I'm liable. Alright, so that's the
position of of Rabbi Yochanan. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, says Abaye, and
this is Ben Zoma, can it be like
the—yes,
let's just read it.
לטעמיה דרב, L’ta’ameih d’Rav, according to Rav,
לא מבעיא שומר חנם שמסר לשומר שכר דעלויי עלייה לשמירתו, lo mibaya
shomer chinam she’masar l’shomer sachar d’iluyei alyah l’shmiraso,
not only if I was a—if I was doing it for free
and then I paid David to watch it, because that's raising the
level of of protection.
If David is being paid, he has higher liability, presumably he's doing
a better job watching it than I am, right? So clear certainly
I didn't violate my responsibility to the original owner. דעלויי עלייה לשמירתו.
d’iluyei alyah l’shmiraso. אלא אפילו שומר שכר שמסר לשומר חנם, ela afilu
shomer sachar she’masar l’shomer chinam, let's say I was being paid by
Eli, שמסר לשומר חנם, she’masar l’shomer chinam, and I gave it to
David and asked David to watch it for free, דגרועי גרעה לשמירתו,
d’garu’ei gar’ah l’shmiraso,
you could say David is not going to do as good of
a job as me because he's not being paid and he's not
as liable. So I actually decreased the assumed level of protection. פטור,
Patur, I am still exempt. Why? מאי טעמא דהא מסרה לבן דעת.
Mai ta’ama d’ha masrah l’ven da’as. I gave it to somebody who's
a responsible party, which means what? Which is an interesting question which
it might mean that that
even though a שומר shomer חנם *Shomer Chinam* has a lower level
of liability than a שומר shomer, שכר *Shomer Sachar*, we're going to
assume that everybody is going to do their best job watching it,
right? Yes, it's true, as a שומר shomer חנם *Shomer Chinam* I
am exempt unless I'm grossly negligent. But does that mean that I'm
going to be irresponsible, sloppy, I'm going to let it get stolen?
I'm going to, oh, well since that's not my level of financial
liability, I don't have to be so careful watching it, right? No,
we should assume that I'm going to watch it as best as
possible. And whether I'm a שומר חנם *Shomer Chinam* or שומר שכר
*Shomer Sachar*, we're all going to do an equally responsible job of
watching it. It's just that if something happens, one person has more
liability than the other. But liability does not translate into the degree
of care. We're going to assume that if you're a responsible adult
and you have somebody else's object under your care, you're going to
do a good job watching it regardless. That seems to be the
assumption. Maybe it's a little too optimistic of a view of human
nature. Okay, but anyway, that's at least my read of מסרה לבן
דעת *Masra L'ben Da'at* means. Okay. ולטעמי דרבי יוחנן *U'letaymi d'Rabbi Yochanan*,
so that's why Rav says even giving it to somebody who is
going to be less liable, it's still not somehow makes me violate
my responsibility to the owner. Okay. ולטעמי דרבי יוחנן *U'letaymi d'Rabbi Yochanan*,
now Rabbi Yochanan who says that I am liable when I give
it to somebody else, לא מיבעיא שומר שכר שמסר לשומר חנם דגרועי
גרעה לשמירתו *lo mibaya Shomer Sachar she'masra l'Shomer Chinam d'gareia l'shmirato*. It
goes without saying that I have violated and am being negligent when
I give it if I'm a paid watcher and I give it
to somebody who's not paid, that lowers the level of protection. אלא
אפילו שומר חנם שמסר לשומר שכר דעלויי עלייה לשמירתו חייב Chayav. *Ela
afilu Shomer Chinam she'masra l'Shomer Sachar de'ali l'shmirato chayav*. Even if I
wasn't being paid and I gave it to somebody who I am
paying, דעלויי עלייה לשמירתו *de'ali l'shmirato*, that's raising the level of protection,
חייב chayav. *chayav*, I'm still liable to the original owner. Why? דאמר
ליה Deamar lei, את לא מהימנת לי בשבועה *D'amar lei ant lo
meimanat li b'shvuata*. I never agreed that anybody else should watch it.
I don't care that you're going to promise me he's going to
do a better job. I don't even care if the likelihood is
that he's going to do a better job. I wanted you to
watch it and I do not want anybody else to watch it.
You have violated your responsibilities to me by giving it under somebody
else's care. Okay? So and that violation of the responsibility is translated
as negligence. And because it's translated as negligence, okay, that means that
as I said, anything now that happens that could somehow be traced
to the fact, attributed to the fact that it was in that
guy's house and not my house, I now have to pay. Yes.
So it's interesting the Talmud doesn't say זכין לאדם שלא בפניו *Zachin
L'adam Shelo Befanav*, right? In other words, it's a זכות *zechut* to
give it to...
No, it's not a זכות *zechut*, because he doesn't, who says he's
okay with somebody else having it? Right, right.
But the whole point is that no, that you know, in one
case according to Rav, David doesn't have a claim, Eli doesn't have
a claim that I've hurt him because I can say I didn't
hurt you, it's equivalent, everybody will do an equally good job watching
it. And the other claim, he doesn't have a, you know, I
don't have a claim to say I was benefiting you because he
could say you're not benefiting me.
If you gave me a really expensive vase to watch in my
house and
I put it in the vault and the vault burns down,
well, the vault at the bank, which isn't me, right, yeah, generally.
Is the question partly like who actually controls the object at that
point? Like if you as the שומר *Shomer* have full control of
the object?
Yeah, but I don't. Maybe in a שוכר socher, *Shocer* or שואל
*Shoel* you could talk more about rights. Okay, but this is a
case of שומר *Shomer*. שומר *Shomer*, I have no rights. I only
have a duty to the owner.
That's the point, meaning they still have full rights of it so
even if you're doing something that's good for it, it's still with
their...
Right, but to some degree I do have latitude to figure out
what I need to do to protect it, right? Like I mean,
you know, if a, whatever, which closet am I going to put
it in, how am I going to wrap it up? So I,
you know, so, but yes, I don't have rights, I have responsibility.
Does it make a difference if you like bring it to David's
property or let's say David just, you know, it's in your house
and you move and David comes and...
Right, so, okay, well it will only make a difference in terms
of the חשבון *cheshbon* of like, could I have said, Dov, if
you were there, yes I know a fire broke out and nothing
could have been done, but I still believe if you were there
you would have been better at running it out of the house
quicker. Yeah, as long as somehow it can be attributed to the
fact that I wasn't there. Okay, let's take a look at the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*.
Okay. Is there a distinction between
trusting somebody's judgment and
trusting...
No, the point, no,
the person you trusted with the object, you don't trust his judgment
that his judgment was this other person would be...
Well, I did trust his judgment, he violated the judgment of that
trust anyway. Okay, let's go. The גמרא *Gemara* says like this: והא
דרב *V'ha d'Rav*, okay, אמר רב חסדא אמר רב חסדא *amar Rav
Chisda amar Rav Chisda*, והא דרב *ha d'Rav*, that statement of Rav
that you're exempt, שומר שמסר לשומר shomer she-masar le-shomer, *Shomer she'masra l'shomer*,
לא בפירוש איתמר אלא מכללא *lo beferush itmar ela mikh'lala*. It was
not said explicitly, it was inferred. דהנהו גינאי *De'hanu ginai*, these gardeners,
דכל יומא הוו מפקדי מרייהו marayehu? גבי דההיא סבתא savta, *de'khol yoma
havai mafkidi maraeihu gabai d'ha savta*, every day they would entrust their
hoes by a certain older woman. יומא חד אפקידינהו גבי חד מינייהו
*Yoma khada afkhidinu gabai chad minaihu*. One day
they all entrusted them by one of them. They all had to
go somewhere and they said to him, one gardener was left behind
and they say, "Here, you watch our shovels." Okay. Now that gardener
that was left behind and watching the shovels, שמע קלא בי הילולא,
he heard the rejoicing at the wedding hall, presumably they all went
to the wedding and they said, "You stay back and you watch
the shovels." Here they were all having a great time. So he
decided, forget this, אזל אפקדינהו לגבי דההיא סבתא, azal apkedinhu legabei dehahi
savta, he went and he took all their shovels and he gave
it to that woman that they usually gave it to, and he
went to be part of the party. אדאזל ואתא, ad-azal ve-ata, when
he went and then came back, איגנוב מרייהו, ignuv marayehu, they were
stolen, okay, from this woman. So he was a שומר שמסר לשומר,
shomer she-masar le-shomer right? He was watching the shovels and he gave
it to this woman. מרייהו? It's a hoe, a
shovel. Okay, אתא לקמיה דרב, ata le-kamei de-Rav, so came to Rav,
ופטריה, u-patrei, Rav exempted him. מאן דחזי סבר man de-chazei savar משום
שומר שמסר לשומר פטור, mishum shomer she-masar le-shomer patur,
the one who saw assumed, "Ah, Rav paskens שומר שמסר לשומר shomer
she-masar le-shomer is exempt." Okay, ולא היא, ve-lo hi, but that's not
really what it was based on. שאני התם דכל יומא נמי אינהו
גופייהו גבי דההיא סבתא הוו מפקדי להו. shani hatam de-chol yoma nami
inhu gufayehu gabei dehahi savta havu mapkedi lehu.
Every day they would give it to this woman so they have
no claim "אין רצוני שיהא פקדוני ביד אחר". ein retzoni she-yehei pikdoni
beyad acher. The whole claim is, "You- I never would have wanted
that person to watch it." We know you were okay with this
person watching it. So that's why that is not even- even who
was it? Rabbi Yochanan would agree in that case you'd be exempt.
But that does not prove that in
general שומר שמסר לשומר shomer she-masar le-shomer, is פטור. patur. Even though
that's the claim that Rav doesn't really hold of it, the גמרא
still thinks that yes, Rav really does hold of it. Okay, we
still do have this debate of שומר שמסר לשומר, shomer she-masar le-shomer.
though the claim here was that if it was based on this
case, then there really isn't a debate. Okay, let's keep on going.
יתיב רבי אמי וקאמר לה להא שמעתא. yativ Rabbi Ami ve-ka'amar lah
le-ha shem'ata. יתיב רבי אמי yativ Rabbi Ami was sitting, telling over
this debate of שומר שמסר לשומר. shomer she-masar le-shomer.
Okay, איתיביה רב אבא בר ממל לרבי אמי. eitiveih Rav Abba bar
Mamal le-Rabbi Ami. So Rav Abba bar Mamal challenged Rabbi Ami. השוכר
פרה מחבירו והשאילה לאחר ומתה כדרכה ישבע השוכר שמתה כדרכה והשואל משלם
לשוכר, ha-socher parah me-chavero ve-hish'ilah le-acher u-metah ke-darkah yishava ha-socher she-metah ke-darkah
ve-ha-sho'el meshalem la-socher, our משנה. Okay. So
the debate here- I swear to Charlie that it died naturally and
David pays me. Okay, so he says like this: ואי איתא, ve-i
ita, now what- how-
I was a שומר שמסר לשומר. I was a שוכר, I gave
it to David. Why do I not now become liable even under
natural death? That issue was a- at giving it over to David
should have made me negligent and been an act of liability. Okay,
ואי איתא, ve-i ita, if it's true that שומר שמסר לשומר חייב,
shomer she-masar le-shomer chayav, לימא ליה, leima lei,
Charlie say to me, "אין רצוני שיהא פקדוני ביד אחר", ein retzoni
she-yehei pikdoni beyad acher, I never wanted anybody else to have it,
and therefore you're liable to me. Now Jenna, the point you made
is a good one because you could say one minute: maybe a
שוכר has more latitude than a שומר. A שומר's whole job is
to serve at the will, you know, serve the interests of the
owner, to protect it. Or whether I serve at the will of
the president, right? So a שוכר, he's a part-owner. He has rights,
not just responsibilities, and maybe that gives him rights to lend out
from, you know, his ownership of the object. The גמרא does not
make that distinction. At the end of the day, it's Charlie's- it's
Charlie's. If Charlie can say to a שומר, "I didn't want anybody
else handling it," he can say to a שוכר, "I don't want
anybody else handling it." That's why if you want somebody else to
drive the car you rent from Hertz, you've got to put them
on the agreement. Okay. So therefore, why in this scenario do I
get off the hook with Charlie? The very giving it to David
should have made me liable. Okay, so the גמרא says "לימא ליה
אין רצוני שיהא פקדוני ביד אחר"? leima lei ein retzoni she-yehei pikdoni
beyad acher? אמר ליה הכא במאי עסקינן, amar lei hacha be-mai askinan,
what are we talking about? בשנתנו לו הבעלים רשות להשאיל. be-shenatnu lo
ha-be'alim reshut le-hash'il.
Charlie explicitly said to me, "David, you have a right to lend
it- you have a light- a right to lend it out if
you want to." Okay. אי הכי, ei hachi, if that's true, לבעלים
בעי לשלומי. la-be'alim ba'ei leshalumei. So naturally we assume when Charlie says
to me I can lend it out, it means I can lend
it out for him. So if I'm lending it out for him,
not sub-lending it, but lending it out the object I bought for
him, then when I lend it to David, David is now directly-
is liable to Charlie. Okay, right. So- so- so גמרא says "אי
הכי לבעלים בעי לשלומי"? ei hachi la-be'alim ba'ei leshalumei? No, no. דאמר
ליה לדעתך. de-amar lei le-da'atcha. No, no. Charlie says to me, "You
can lend it out for yourself," meaning you can sub-lend it. Okay,
it's yours for the next hundred days and if you want to
lend it out to your friend, you can sub-lend it, okay, I-
sort of, you know, in terms of your ownership, sub-lending your ownership
to it, you can do that. And that creates this link that
David is liable to me and I am liable to Charlie and
I did not violate Charlie's interests by lending it out. Okay. מתיב
רמי בר חמא, metiv Rami bar Chama, Rami bar Chama asked, "המפקיד
מעות אצל חבירו, ha-mapkid ma'ot etzel chavero, okay, if somebody entrusts money
to someone,
צרן והשליכן לאחוריו, tzaran ve-hishlichan le-achorav, he binds them in a pouch
and throws them behind his back,
או שמסרן לבנו ובתו הקטנים, o she-masaran li-vno u-vito ha-ketanim, or gives
it to his minor children, ונעל בפניהם שלא כראוי, ve-na'al bifneihem she-lo
ke-ra'ui, and he locked the door in front of his minor children
but without really locking it like you know, like-" they can get
out anyway through the back door or something, חייב. chayav. So those
are not considered legitimate, you know, good ways of protecting money. שלא
שמר כדרך השומרים, Shelo shamar kederech hashomrim, you did not do the
normal way a שומר protects money. So טעמא דקתני. Taama dektani. The
reason is because I gave it to my underage children that I
am חייב. chayav. הא
גדולים, Ha gedolim, if I gave it to responsible adults, פטור, patur,
I am exempt. אמאי? Amai? Why? נימא ליה אין רצוני שיהא פקדוני
ביד אחר, Neima lei ein retzoni sheyehei pikdoni beyad acher, say I
don't want somebody else to be handling it. אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
כל המפקיד
על דעת אשתו ובניו הוא דמפקיד. Kol hamaphkid al daat ishto uvanav
hu demaphkid. Anybody that entrusts money to someone understands that that person
might ask his wife or kids, adult children, to watch it, and
is implicitly okay. It's sort of like the story about the older
woman, right?
I implicitly understand, you know, and I can't say I didn't want
them to watch it. That sort of came with the deal, okay?
If Eli says to me, Dov, I want you to take this
home and watch it, it doesn't mean that I can't leave it
home with my wife and I have to keep it on me
the whole time. That's understood. Okay, as long as... so that's the
argument, that's an exception like the case of the older woman being
an exception in
regards to giving it to somebody else, that has to be explicit.
Right, somebody exactly. And minor children is anyway irresponsible because they're minors.
אמרי נהרדעי, Amri Nehardei, דיקא נמי דקתני, Deika nami dektani, it also
can be inferred because it says, או שמסר לבנו ובתו הקטנים חייב,
O shemasar livno uvito haktanim chayav, younger, younger kids. הא לבנו ובתו
הגדולים פטור, Ha livno uvito hagedolim patur, older children you'd be exempt.
But why are we talking about children? Why didn't it just say
minors? מכלל דאחרים, Michlal deacherim, if they were not your children, they
were just strangers, לא שנא גדולים ולא שנא קטנים חייב, Lo shena
gedolim velo shena ktanim chayav, it wouldn't matter adults or children, חייב.
דאם כן, Deim ken, because if it really were the question of
adult versus child, ליתני סתמא, Lisni stama, just say if I gave
it to a minor to watch. The fact that it says minor
child means that my children is basically okay as long as they're
adults, because they're my children. שמע מינה. Shema mina. That's a good
inference. Okay, אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so we've got this nice debate,
and now Michael, you can be very happy, we're going to פסקן.
pasken. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, הלכתא, Hilchesa, the הלכה is, שומר שמסר
לשומר חייב. Shomer shemasar leshomer chayav. You're חייב. לא מבעיא שומר שכר
שמסר לשומר חנם חייב, Lo mibaya shomer sachar shemasar leshomer chinam chayav,
not only if a paid guardian gives it to a free one,
to a who's unpaid, גרועי גרעיה לשמירתו, Geruei garayei lishmiraso, you lower
the level, אלא אפילו שומר חנם שמסר לשומר שכר חייב, Ela afilu
shomer chinam shemasar leshomer sachar chayav, even if you give it to
somebody you paid more money. מאי טעמא? Mai taama? Not for the
reason everybody's been saying until now. רבא Rava פסקנ'ס paskens this way
but for a different reason: דאמר ליה, because Eli can say to
me, את מהימנת לי בשבועה, At meheimnat li bishvua, Dov, I trust
your oath to me about what happens to it, האי לא מהימן
לי בשבועה, Hai lo meheiman li bishvua, I do not trust the
other guy's oath what happens to it, and therefore giving it to
him doesn't mean he's liable to me, it means that you have
violated your responsibility to me because now I can't get an oath
from you about what happened to it, and therefore I can never
be certain and really trust what happened to it. So by putting
me in that situation, you have been negligent to me and you're
liable now for what happens. Now the נפקא מינה Nafka mina of
these two reasons is, is that if I directly witnessed what happened
and can make the oath to the original owner, then I still
do remain off the hook. Okay, so we're going to see about
that in the גמרא, okay, or about cases in which cases in
which the claim 'I don't trust his oath, I only trust your
oath' is a different type of a claim than 'I don't want
anybody else handling my object.'
Well no, the סבתא, they do implicitly trust her oath and they
trust her to watch it. So tomorrow we're going to begin the
next topic which will circle back to this one, but the next
topic will be תחלתה בפשיעה וסופה באונס, Techilato bipshia vesofo beones, because
I hope you can all appreciate that the point here was to
say that I was negligent by giving it out. Well why does
that initial negligence make me liable if it just סתם stam dies?
Okay, so that ultimately circles back to the idea, since that original
act of giving it was a negligence, I'm going to be liable
for what happens afterwards, which is תחלתה בפשיעה וסופה באונס. Techilato bipshia
vesofo beones. So that's what we're going to look at tomorrow. Okay?